<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- **************************************************************************
.... For copyright and licensing terms, see the file named COPYING.
.... **************************************************************************
.-->
<?xml-stylesheet href="docbook-xml.css" type="text/css"?>

<refentry id="oom-kill-protect">

<refmeta xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<refentrytitle>oom-kill-protect</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class="manual">user commands</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class="source">nosh</refmiscinfo>
<xi:include href="version.xml" />
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
<refname>oom-kill-protect</refname>
<refpurpose>set the protection level against the kernel's Out Of Memory Killer</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsynopsisdiv>
<cmdsynopsis>
<command>oom-kill-protect</command> 
<arg choice='req'><replaceable>level</replaceable></arg> 
<arg choice='req'><replaceable>next-prog</replaceable></arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsection><title>Description</title>

<para>
<command>oom-kill-protect</command> is a chain-loading utility that sets the OOM Kill protection according to <replaceable>level</replaceable> and then chain loads to <replaceable>next-prog</replaceable> with the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>execvp</refentrytitle><manvolnum>3</manvolnum></citerefentry> function.  
</para>

<para>
<replaceable>next-prog</replaceable> may contain its own command line options, which <command>oom-kill-protect</command> will ignore.
</para>

<para>
If <replaceable>level</replaceable> is the literal value <code>fromenv</code> (in lowercase) then <command>oom-kill-protect</command> locates the <envar>oomprotect</envar> environment variable and replaces <replaceable>level</replaceable> with its value.
This is a special mechanism for enabling <citerefentry><refentrytitle>rcctl</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> (a.k.a. <citerefentry><refentrytitle>system-control</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> <command>set-service-env</command>) to control the OOM Kill protection settings of services by setting an <envar>oomprotect</envar> variable for each service.
</para>

<para>
Otherwise, <replaceable>level</replaceable> can be the literal values <code>true</code>, <code>false</code>, <code>on</code>, <code>off</code>, <code>yes</code>, <code>no</code>, or a signed decimal integer.
The literal integer is a Linux-style OOM Score adjustment.
The others are boolean flag states.
</para>

<para>
On BSDs, OOM Killer protection is a binary value; it is either on or off for a process.
The boolean settings map directly.
The OOM Score adjustment is mapped such that a value equal to or less than -1000 implies that protection is on; and higher values imply that protection is off.
This is on the grounds that any value greater than -1000 does not protect against the OOM Killer, but merely adjusts how likely an unprotected process is to be selected for termination.
</para>

<para>
On Linux, the decimal integer is simply an OOM Score.
The binary values map to -1000 for false, and 0 for true.
This is on the grounds that -1000 completely protects against the OOM Killer.
</para>

</refsection>

<refsection><title>Author</title>
<para><author><personname><firstname>Jonathan</firstname> <surname>de Boyne Pollard</surname></personname></author></para>
</refsection>

</refentry>
