<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- **************************************************************************
.... For copyright and licensing terms, see the file named COPYING.
.... **************************************************************************
.-->
<?xml-stylesheet href="docbook-xml.css" type="text/css"?>

<refentry id="open-controlling-tty">

<refmeta xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<refentrytitle>open-controlling-tty</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class="manual">user commands</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class="source">nosh</refmiscinfo>
<xi:include href="version.xml" />
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
<refname>open-controlling-tty</refname>
<refpurpose>open a controlling terminal and prepare for login</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsynopsisdiv>
<refsection><title>BSD</title>
<cmdsynopsis>
<command>open-controlling-tty</command> 
<arg choice='opt'>--revoke</arg> 
<arg choice='opt'>--exclusive</arg> 
<arg choice='req'><replaceable>next-prog</replaceable></arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</refsection><refsection><title>Linux</title>
<cmdsynopsis>
<command>open-controlling-tty</command> 
<arg choice='opt'>--vhangup</arg> 
<arg choice='opt'>--exclusive</arg> 
<arg choice='req'><replaceable>next-prog</replaceable></arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</refsection>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsection><title>Description</title>

<para>
<command>open-controlling-tty</command> is a chain-loading utility that opens a terminal as a controlling terminal, sets its own standard I/O file descriptors to it, and then chain loads to <replaceable>next-prog</replaceable> with the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>execvp</refentrytitle><manvolnum>3</manvolnum></citerefentry> function.  
</para>

<para>
<replaceable>next-prog</replaceable> may contain its own command line options, which <command>open-controlling-tty</command> will ignore.
</para>

<para>
<command>open-controlling-tty</command> expects to inherit the terminal character device filename to open as the value of the <envar>TTY</envar> environment variable, which it expects to have been set up by a program such as <citerefentry><refentrytitle>vc-get-tty</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> or <citerefentry><refentrytitle>pty-get-tty</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>.  
This can be either a virtual or a real terminal.
It opens this terminal, hangs up (or otherwise disassociates) any existing processes for which it was still a controlling terminal or which had open file handles to it; assigns it as its own controlling terminal; sets its own standard input, standard output, and standard error file descriptors to it (closing whatever they were previously open to); and then (if everything succeeds) chain loads <replaceable>next-prog</replaceable>.
</para>

<para>
The standard file descriptors are duplicated from an open file descriptor to the terminal, which is opened in read+write mode.
There is one underlying common file description.
</para>

<para>
<command>open-controlling-tty</command> does not call <citerefentry><refentrytitle>setsid</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum></citerefentry> to become a session leader.
On some operating systems it it necessary to already be a session leader in order to set a controlling terminal.
On those operating systems, it is thus necessary to chain to <command>open-controlling-tty</command> from <citerefentry><refentrytitle>setsid</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>.
</para>

<para>
<command>open-controlling-tty</command> does not make any attempt to adjust its process group or the foreground process group of the controlling terminal.
Dealing with these is the province of a job-control shell, which may not even run as this process.
(Linux <citerefentry><refentrytitle>login</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> with PAM runs the job-controlling shell as a child process, for example.)
</para>

<para>
If the <arg choice='plain'>--exclusive</arg> command line option is used, it will attempt to use the <code>TIOCEXCL</code> <citerefentry><refentrytitle>ioctl</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum></citerefentry> function to put the terminal device into "exclusive" mode.
</para>

</refsection><refsection><title>Security</title>

<refsection><title>Linux</title>

<para>
If <arg choice='plain'>--vhangup</arg> command line option is used, which tells it to call the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>vhangup</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum></citerefentry> system call, <command>open-controlling-tty</command> has to open the terminal device file twice, once so that it can disconnect/hangup existing processes, which of course disconnects itself at the same time, and once again to gain the controlling TTY afterwards.
There is a race condition here, where the character device file could be unlinked or otherwise altered in between the two opens.
</para>

</refsection><refsection><title>BSD</title>

<para>
<command>open-controlling-tty</command> opens the terminal device file once, because BSD has no <citerefentry><refentrytitle>vhangup</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum></citerefentry> system call.
Instead, on BSD <command>open-controlling-tty</command> calls <citerefentry><refentrytitle>revoke</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum></citerefentry> before opening the terminal device file, if the <arg choice='plain'>--revoke</arg> command line option is used.
A similar race condition exists, except that it is between the call to <citerefentry><refentrytitle>revoke</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum></citerefentry> and the call to then <citerefentry><refentrytitle>open</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum></citerefentry> the terminal device file.
Again, the character device file could be unlinked or otherwise altered in between the two.
</para>

</refsection>

<para>
To restrict the processes able to take advantage of these races to just those programs running as the current user or the superuser:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
System administrators should ensure that the directory containing the character device file is not writable by untrusted accounts.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Programs that invoke <command>open-controlling-tty</command> should ensure that the character device file is owned by the effective UID of the process, and has <code>rw-</code> permissions for that owner alone, no other user or group having any permissions.
</para><para>
The <citerefentry><refentrytitle>grantpt</refentrytitle><manvolnum>3</manvolnum></citerefentry> library function does this for pseudo-terminals.
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>pty-get-tty</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> calls this function; and <citerefentry><refentrytitle>vc-get-tty</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> performs the moral equivalent for virtual consoles.
(On the BSDs, pseudo-terminal slave devices are created with these UID and permissions in the first place, and the library function is in fact a no-op.)
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Programs that invoke <command>open-controlling-tty</command> should ensure that neither it nor any other program can open the character device file until the ownership has been properly set.
</para><para>
The <citerefentry><refentrytitle>unlockpt</refentrytitle><manvolnum>3</manvolnum></citerefentry> library function does this for pseudo-terminals.
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>pty-get-tty</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> calls this function.
(On the BSDs, because <citerefentry><refentrytitle>grantpt</refentrytitle><manvolnum>3</manvolnum></citerefentry> is a no-op, this is a no-op as well.)
Unfortunately, there is no moral equivalent for kernel-supplied virtual consoles, and nothing that <citerefentry><refentrytitle>vc-get-tty</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> can do.
However, userspace virtual consoles use pseudo-terminals and <citerefentry><refentrytitle>pty-get-tty</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>.  </para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</refsection><refsection><title>Author</title>
<para><author><personname><firstname>Jonathan</firstname> <surname>de Boyne Pollard</surname></personname></author></para>
</refsection>

</refentry>
