<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- **************************************************************************
.... For copyright and licensing terms, see the file named COPYING.
.... **************************************************************************
.-->
<?xml-stylesheet href="docbook-xml.css" type="text/css"?>

<refentry id="pty-run">

<refmeta xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<refentrytitle>pty-run</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class="manual">user commands</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class="source">nosh</refmiscinfo>
<xi:include href="version.xml" />
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
<refname>pty-run</refname>
<refpurpose>run a program under a pseudo-terminal </refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsynopsisdiv>
<cmdsynopsis>
<command>pty-run</command>
<arg choice='opt'>-t</arg>
<arg choice='req'><replaceable>next-prog</replaceable></arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsection><title>Description</title>

<para>
<command>pty-run</command> is a utility that expects file descriptor 4 to be the master side of a pseudo-terminal and the <envar>TTY</envar> environment variable to be the full device filename of the slave side.
(<citerefentry><refentrytitle>pty-get-tty</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> can be used to set this process state up.)
</para>

<para>
It spawns <replaceable>next-prog</replaceable>, closing the master side file descriptor in the child process, and then enters a loop where it simultaneously:
</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>
<para>
writes all data received from the master side to its own standard output, until the master side signals hangup (i.e. when the line discipline would set modem control lines, as it would on a real serial device, to signal hangup because the last slave file descriptor is closed);
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
writes all data received from its standard input to the master side, until its standard input signals EOF with a 0 byte read; and
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
acts upon state changes in the spawned child process.
</para>
</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<para>
It has two modes:
</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>
<para>
If the <arg choice='plain'>-t</arg> option was used, it behaves in "pass-through TTY" mode.
</para>

<para>
It copies the terminal mode settings from its standard input or output to the pseudo-terminal and sets both its standard input and output to "raw" mode.
If the child process stops with a stop signal, it undoes this and stops itself.
When it receives a <code>SIGCONT</code>, it re-does it and sends a <code>SIGCONT</code> to its child.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
In the default if the <arg choice='plain'>-t</arg> option is not used, it behaves in "pipe" mode.
</para>

<para>
It makes no alteration to terminal mode settings.
If the child process stops with a stop signal, it simply sends it a <code>SIGCONT</code> immediately.
</para>
</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<para>
<replaceable>next-prog</replaceable> may contain its own command line options, which <command>pty-run</command> will ignore.
</para>

</refsection><refsection><title>Security</title>

<para>
<command>pty-run</command> does not touch the slave side device at all.
The slave device race condition that must be avoided for <citerefentry><refentrytitle>open-controlling-tty</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> (q.v.) and similar slave-side programs should have already been handled by whatever created the pseudo-terminal (e.g. <citerefentry><refentrytitle>pty-get-tty</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>).
</para>

</refsection>
<refsection><title>See also</title>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>console-terminal-emulator</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>an I/O pump that pumps data in both directions between the master side of a pseudo-terminal and an abstraction of a virtual terminal's display and human input device hardwares</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</refsection>

<refsection><title>Author</title>
<para><author><personname><firstname>Jonathan</firstname> <surname>de Boyne Pollard</surname></personname></author></para>
</refsection>

</refentry>
