<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- **************************************************************************
.... For copyright and licensing terms, see the file named COPYING.
.... **************************************************************************
.-->
<?xml-stylesheet href="docbook-xml.css" type="text/css"?>

<refentry id="set-dynamic-hostname">

<refmeta xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<refentrytitle>set-dynamic-hostname</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class="manual">user commands</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class="source">nosh</refmiscinfo>
<xi:include href="version.xml" />
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
<refname>set-dynamic-hostname</refname>
<refpurpose>set the dynamic hostname from the statically configured hostname</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsynopsisdiv>
<cmdsynopsis>
<command>set-dynamic-hostname</command>
<arg choice="opt">--force</arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsection><title>Description</title>

<para>
<command>set-dynamic-hostname</command> sets the dynamic hostname from the statically configured hostname.
It is designed to be run as part of system or container/jail initialization.
</para>

<para>
The dynamic hostname is the hostname that is returned from the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>gethostname</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum></citerefentry> library function, which may vary during the system's lifetime as the machine is (for example) granted DHCP leases.
On operating systems such as FreeBSD, OpenBSD, and Linux, the dynamic hostname is the same as the nodename that is returned by the the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>uname</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum></citerefentry> library function (although the POSIX standard does not in fact require this).
</para>

<para>
The statically configured hostname is the value of the <envar>hostname</envar> environment variable that the <command>set-dynamic-hostname</command> program is started with.
Normally, <command>set-dynamic-hostname</command> will be chain-loaded from something like <citerefentry><refentrytitle>envdir</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> reading <envar>hostname</envar> out of an environment directory or <citerefentry><refentrytitle>read-conf</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> reading it from a file such as <filename>/etc/rc.conf</filename>.
</para>

<para>
If that environment variable is missing, <command>set-dynamic-hostname</command> looks (on operating systems that support it) to the kernel environment variable <envar>dhcp.host-name</envar>, which is the host name contained in the DHCP lease obtained by a PXE boot loader.
If that fails, it sets the dynamic hostname to <quote><code>localhost</code></quote>.
</para>

<para>
Unless the <arg choice="plain">--force</arg> option is used, <command>set-dynamic-hostname</command> will not attempt to set the dynamic hostname if it has already been set to something.
Thus setting the dynamic hostname for a container/jail can be done by simply setting it as the jail is created.
Any later execution of <command>set-dynamic-hostname</command> within the jail, as part of its startup process, will not override that.
</para>

<para>
No restrictions are placed upon hostnames by <command>set-dynamic-hostname</command>, nor by most operating systems, except length restrictions.
However, for best results, administrators should obey the rules set out in RFC 1123 &#x00A7; 2.1, which limit hostnames to:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
the characters 
<code>A</code>&#x2013;<code>Z</code>, 
<code>a</code>&#x2013;<code>z</code>, 
<code>0</code>&#x2013;<code>9</code>, 
<code>.</code>, and
<code>-</code>
(preferring lowercase, since RFC 1123 Host Names are not case sensitive) with the first character not being either <code>.</code> or <code>-</code> and the last character not being <code>.</code>
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
a maximum of 63 characters (hostnames here being the initial label(s) of an RFC 1123 Host Name)
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
For clarity, observe that a RFC 1123 Host Name comprises two parts:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
the dynamic hostname, as set by this command, comprising the initial one or more labels (usually only the first label); and
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
the domain name, as returned by the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>getdomainname</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum></citerefentry> library function (and on Linux the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>uname</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum></citerefentry> library function), comprising the remaining labels.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</refsection><refsection><title>Author</title>
<para><author><personname><firstname>Jonathan</firstname> <surname>de Boyne Pollard</surname></personname></author></para>
</refsection>

</refentry>
